Guide to the Arvid Paulson Papers 1875-1977 MSS.043
Fales Library and Special Collections
Arvid Paulson Papers
1875-1977
Fales Library and Special Collections
Paulson, Arvid
MSS.043
8.5 Linear Feet (21 boxes)
The Arvid Paulson Papers represent Paulson's attempts to bring the work of August Strindberg and Henrik Ibsen to a twentieth century American public. The collection contains his correspondence with actors, publishers and producers, the manuscripts of his translations, some of his published criticism on Strindberg and Ibsen as well as that of other authors. Finally, it contains miscellaneous theatre memorabilia culled from a long life spent going to the theatre, perfoming in plays and occasionally even producing them himself.
Provenance
Arvid Paulson donated his collection of rare and first editions of August Strindberg's writings to the Fales Library in 1970. His papers, consisting of eight linear feet of correspondence, manuscripts, printed material and memorabilia, were given over a period of years from 1970 until his death in Malmo, Sweden, in 1977.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Biography of Arvid Paulson
Arvid Paulson (1888-1977) was an author, translator and actor. Born in Helsingborg, Sweden, he emigrated to the United States in 1904. Though he performed in many plays written by Strindberg and Ibsen, he is perhaps best known as a translator of their work.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Correspondence contains Paulson's correspondence with various producers, actors and publishers, 1917-1977.
Series II: Manuscripts contains the manuscripts for Paulson's translations of Ibsen, Strindberg and other Scandinavian writers; it also contains Paulson's collection of Ibsen ephemera.
Series III: Publications contains Paulson's and other writers' published articles about Strindberg.
Series IV: Printed Matter and Memorabilia contains programs, playbills, photographs and miscellaneous other material relating to productions of Strindberg's and Ibsen's plays in Sweden and America, as well as more generally to the twentieth century American theatre.
Series V: Paulson contains some of Paulson's personal papers.
Arrangement
The collection has been organized into five Series. Each series initiates a new numbering sequence. Oversize material is listed toward the end of the collection.
Missing Title
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Manuscripts
Series III: Publications
Series IV: Printed Matter and Memorabilia
Series V: Paulson's Personal Papers
Oversize
Separated Material
In addition to the material found here, Arvid Paulson also donated some 350 books and articles by and about Strindberg and Henrik Ibsen to the Fales Library. The following books and articles have been separated from the collection and are individually catalogued through BobCat.
First Editions, Swedish
Strindberg, August Abu Casems Tofflor 1908
Amerikanska Humorister 1878
Dagsländan 1885
Bibliska Egennamn med Ordfränder 1910
Bjälbo-Jarlen: Skådespel i Fem Akter 1909
Carl XII: Skådespel i Fem Tablåer 1901
Czarens Kurir, eller Sågfilarens Hemlighet 1912
Till Damaskus I-II, 1898
Det Nya Riket 1882
Dikter 1883
1885: Revy i Litterära och Sociala Frågor 1885
Engelbrekt: Skådespel i Fyra Akter 1901
Ensam 1903
Erik XIV: Skådespel i Fyra Akter 1899
Fagervik och Skamsund 1902
Författaren Stockholm 1909
Från Fjärdingen och Svartbäcken 1877
Framtiden: Tidskrift för Fosterländsk Odling 1878
Gamla Stockholm 1882
Giftas: Tolv Äktenskapshistorier 1884
Gillets hemligheter 1880
Gustav Adolf: Schauspiel in Fünf Akten 1901
I Havsbandet 1890
Han och Hon 1919
Himmelrikets Nycklar 1892
Jardin des Plantes 1896
Kina och Japan 1911
Kulturhistoriska Studier 1881
"Likställighet och Tyranni" Ur Dagens Krönika 1885
Likt och Olikt 1884
Mäster Olof: Skådespel i Fem Akter; Lycko-Pers Resa 1872
Memorandum till Medlemmarna av Intima Teatern 1908
Midsommar 1901
Modersmålets Anor n.d
Nya Svenska Öden 1906
I Rom 1870
Samvetskval 1899
Shakespeares Macbeth... 1909
Sista Riddaren 1908
Skärkarlsliv 1888
Somngångarnätter 1884
Svanevit 1914
Svarta Fanor 1907
Svenska Folket Vol. I, 1882
Svenska Folket Vol. II, 1882
Tal till den Svenska Nationen 1910
Taklagsöl. Syndabocken: Två Berättelser 1907
Tjensteqvinnans Son Vol. I, 1886
Tjensteqvinnans Son Vol. II, 1886
Tjensteqvinnans Son Vol. III, 1887
Tryckt och Otryckt Vol. I, 1897
Tryckt och Otryckt Vol. II, 1897
Tryckt och Otryckt Vol. III, 1897
Tschandala: En Berättelse 1897
Typer och Prototyper inom Mineralkemien 1898
Utopier i Verkligheten 1885
Världsspråkens Rötter 1911
Vid Högre Rätt 1899
First Editions: French, German, Portuguese
Der Bewusste Wille in der Weltgeschichte 1903
Bohème Suédoise 1894
Fraulino Julie 1908
Die Leute auf Hemsö n.d.
Der Romantische Rüster auf Rånö 1921
Editions General
Single Copies
The Chamber Plays 1962
Créanciers 1959
The Dance of Death I-II, 1971
Days of Loneliness 1971
Ehegeschichten n.d.
Motherlove 1969
Die Gespenstersonate n.d.
Getting Married 1971
The Great Highway 1954
I Hafsbandet 1908
Himmelrikets Nycklar 1962
The Last of the Knights; The Regent; Earl Birger of Bjälbo 1956
Lui et elle 1965
Vasaarvet och andra berättelser 1916
Dans les Iles 1909
Det Nya Riket: Satiriska Skildringar 1882
Ordet i Min Makt: Läsebok for underklassen 1968
En ovälkommen 1972
Påsk 1910
Riksföreståndaren 1909
Den Romantiske Klockaren på Rånö 1913
The Saga of the Folkungs; Engelbrekt 1959
Skärkarlslif 1907
Stora Landsvägen; Abu Casems Tofflor 1924
Die Stadtreise und andere Gedichte 1970
The Stronger 1970
There are Crimes and Crimes 1912
The Vasa Trilogy 1959
I Vårbrytningen 1908
Ur Ockulta Dagboken 1963
Multiple Copies
The Cloister n.d.
The Cloister 1969
Klostret 1966
L'Abbaye 1962
A Dream Play 1971
A Dream Play (Japanese) n.d.
Ein Traumspiel 1963
Gustav Adolf 1957
Gustav Adolf: Skådespel i Fem Akter 1900
A Madman's Defense n.d.
Le plaidoyer d'un fou 1968
En Dåres Försvarstal; Oväder (Japanese) n.d
Miss Julia; The Stronger 1912
Miss Julie 1961
Miss Julie 1965
Miss Julie; The Ghost Sonata 1967
Mademoiselle Julie n.d.
Mademoiselle Julie 1957
Fräulein Julie 1955
Hemsöborna 1913
Hemsöborna 1945
Hemsöborna 1959
The People of Hemsö 1959
The Natives of Hemsö n.d
The Natives of Hemsö; The Stranger 1967
Père 1888
Père 1958
Röda Rummet 1880
Röda Rummet 1908
La Sala Rossa 1956
The Road to Damascus: A Trilogy 1958
The Road to Damascus: A Trilogy 1960
Till Damaskus 1966
The Scapegoat 1962
The Scapegoat 1967
Anthologies
August Strindberg: The Strindberg Reader 1968
Eight Expressionist Plays 1965
Eight Famous Plays 1949
Plays 1912
Plays 1916
Plays 1912
Seven Plays by Strindberg 1964
Six Plays of Strindberg 1955
Strindberg's One-Act Plays 1969
Strindberg's Queen Christina, Charles XII, Gustav III 1955
World Historical Plays: August Strindberg Vol. 6, 1970
Correspondence
Strindberg, August August Strindbergs och Ola Hanssons Brevväxling: 1888-1892 1938
De återfunna breven till Harriet Bosse 1955
Strindbergs Brev till Harriet Bosse 1932
Berendsohn, Walter A. Briefe an Strindberg 1967
Eklund, Torsten, Ed. From an Occult Diary: Marriage with Harriet Bosse 1965
Eklund, Torsten, Ed. Strindbergs Brev Vol. I, 1948
Eklund, Torsten, Ed. Strindbergs Brev Vol. II, 1950
Eklund, Torsten, Ed. Strindbergs Brev Vol. III,1952
Eklund, Torsten, Ed. Strindbergs Brev Vol. IV, 1952
Lundegård, Axel Några Strindbergsminnen: Knutna till en handfull brev 1920
Paul, Adolf Strindberg: Erinnerungen und Briefe 1914
Paulson, Arvid, Ed. Letters of Strindberg to Harriet Bosse: Love Letters from a Tormented Genius 1959 (2x)
Schering, Emil Strindberg: Briefe an Emil Schering 1924
Multi-Volume Collected Editions
1. August Strindbergs Werke
Strindberg, August Strindberg: Dramaturgie 1911
Dramen 1911
Schweizer Novellen 1912
Nach Damaskus: I-III 1921
2. Kammarspel, Opus 1-5
Strindberg, August Svarta Handsken 1909
Pelikanen 1907
Spök-Sonaten 1907
Brända Tomten 1907
Oväder 1907
3. Samlade Dramatiska Arbeten 1903
4. Samlade Otryckta Skrifter Vol. I-II, 1918-1919
5. Samlade Skrifter
Ungdomsdramer Vol. I, 1912
Mäster Olof Vol. II, 1912
I Vårbrytningen Vol. III, 1912
Kulturhistoriska Studier Vol. IV, 1912
Röda Rummet Vol. V, 1918
Gamla Stockholm Vol. VI, 1918
Svenska Folket Vol. VII, 1912
Svenska Folket Vol. VIII, 1912
Tidiga '80-tals dramer Vol. IX, 1918
Det Nya Riket Vol. X, 1918
Svenska Öden och Äventyr Vol. XI, 1918
Svenska Öden och Äventyr Vol. XII, 1918
Dikter Vol. XIII, 1918
Giftas Vol. XIV. 1918
Utopier i verkligheten Vol. XV, 1919
Likt och Olikt Vol. XVI, 1913
Likt och Olikt Vol. XVII, 1913
Tjänstekvinnans son Vol. XVIII, 1918
Tjänstekvinnans son Vol.XIX, 1919
Bland Franska Bönder Vol. XX, 1914
Hemsöborna och Skärkarlsliv Vol. 21, 1918
Prosabitar Vol. 22, 1918
Naturalistiska Sorgespel Vol 23, 1914
I havsbandet Vol 24, 1914
Komedier och enaktare Vol 25, 1918
En dåres försvarstal Vol 26, 1918
Prosabitar Vol. 27, 1919
Inferno och Legender Vol. 28, 1919
Till Damaskus Vol. 29, 1918
Vid Högre Rätt Vol. 30, 1915
Folkungasagan, Gustav Vasa, Erik XIV Vol. 31, 1918
Gustav Adolf Vol. 32, 1915
Kaspers Fet-Tisdag Vol. 33, 1915
Dödsdansen Vol. 34, 1920
Engelbrecht; Carl XII Vol. 35, 1918
Kronbruden Vol. 36, 1918
Fagervik och Skamsund Vol. 37, 1918
Sagor och Ensam Vol. 38, 1916
Näktergalen i Wittenberg Vol. 39, 1916
Götiska Rummen Vol. 40, 1916
Svarta Fanor Vol. 41, 1916
Historiska Miniatyrer Vol. 42, 1917 (2x)
Hövdingaminnen Vol. 43, 1917
Taklagsöl; Syndabocken Vol. 44, 1917
Kammarspel Vol. 45, 1919
En Blå Bok Vol. 46, 1918
En Blå Bok Vol. 47, 1918
En Blå Bok Vol. 48, 1918
Siste Riddaren; Riksföreståndaren; Bjälbo-Jarlen Vol. 49, 1918
Öppna Brev till Intima Teatern Vol. 50, 1921
Stora Landsvägen; Abu Cassems Tofflor Vol. 51, 1921
Språkvetenskapliga Studier Vol. 52, 1920
Tal till Svenska Nationen Vol. 53, 1919
Efterslåtter Vol. 54, 1920
Han och Hon Vol. 55, 1921
6. Skrifter av August Strindberg
Historiska Dramer Vol. 10, 1946
Lyriska Dramer Vol. 11 1946
Samtidsdramer Vol. 12, 1946
7. Stockholm Radiotjänsts Teaterbibliotek no. 83-89
Mäster Olof, Moderskärlek, Till Damaskus: Första Delen, Dödsdansen: Första Delen, Ett Drömspel, Pelikanen, Stora Landsvägen No. 83-89, 1948.
8. Théatre No. 1-8, 1958-1962
Camarades, Paria, Devant la mort, Il ne faut pas jouer avec le feu, Le Lien No. 1, 1958
L'Avent, Crime et crime, Pâques No. 2, 1958
Charles XII, La Reine Christine, Gustave III no. 3, 1960
La Danse de Mort No. 4, 1960
Le Songe, Le Hollandais, Les Babouches d'Abou Kassem, La Grand'route No. 5, 1960
Orage, La Maison Brulée, La Sonate des Spectres, Le Pélican, Le Gant Noir, L'Ile des Morts No. 6, 1961
La Saga des Folkungar, Gustave Vasa No. 7, 1961
Le Voyage de Pierre L'Heureux, La Plus forte, Les Clefs du Ciel, Premier avertissement, Doit et avoir, Amour maternel No. 8, 1962
Secondary
Ahlström, Stellan. Strindbergs erövring av Paris 1956
Ahlström, Stellan; Eklund, Torsten August Strindberg: Mannaår och ålderdom 1911
Andersson, Elis August Strindberg: tal vid minnesfesten 1949
Babillotte, Arthur August Strindberg: Das Hohe Lied Seines Lebens 1910
Berendsohn, Walter A. Strindbergsproblem 1946
Berendsohn, Walter A. "August Strindbergs autobiographische Schriften." Scandinavica 5:1 (1966)
Berendsohn, Walter A. August Strindberg als Meister der Bühnenkunst n.d.
Berendsohn, Walter A. August Strindberg: Ein geborener Dramatiker 1956
Berendsohn, Walter A. "August Strindberg und die Frauen." Sonderdruck aus den Lübeckischen Blättern 9-10 (1965)
Berendsohn, Walter A. "August Strindbergs berättelse Stråmannen." Samfundet Örebro stads och länsbiblioteks vänners meddelande 25 (1967)
Berendsohn, Walter A. August Strindbergs Parisschilderungen n.d.
Berendsohn, Walter A. August Strindbergs skärgårds och Stockholmsskildringar 1962
Berendsohn, Walter A. "Goethe och Strindberg." Särtryck ur Samlaren 1949
Berendsohn, Walter A. "The Oriental Studies of August Strindberg." Central Asian Collectanea 5 (1960)
Berendsohn, Walter A. Strindberg och Birger Mörner i Brevväxling 1946
Berendsohn, Walter A. Strindbergs Schauspiele aus der Schwedischen Geschichte n.d.
Berendsohn, Walter A. Strindbergs sista levnadsår 1948
Berendsohn, Walter A. "Studier i manuskriptet till Strindbergs 'Karantänmästarens andra berättelse.'" Särtryck ur Samlaren 1951
Bjurström, Per Teaterdekoration i Sverige 1964
Björck, Albert Emmanuel Swedenborg, August Strindberg och Det Ondas problem 1898
Børge, Vagn Kvinden i Strindbergs Liv og Digtning 1936
Brandell, Gunnar Strindbergs Infernokris 1950
Brandell, Gunnar På Stindbergs vägar genom Frankrike 1949
Brunius, August Ansikten och Masker 1917
Brustein, Robert The Theatre of Revolt 1964
Claussen, Christian En Digterskjaebne 1913
Drachmann, Holger En Bok om Strindberg 1894
Edquist, Sven Samhällets fiende: En Strindbergsstudie 1961
Eklund, Torsten. Ed. Strindberg i Blå Tornet n.d.
Engström, Albert August Strindberg och jag 1923
Erdmann, Nils August Strindberg: Från Klara Skola till Röda Rummet Vol. 1, 1920
Erdmann, Nils August Strindberg: Genom Skärselden till Korset Vol. 2, 1920
Esswein, Hermann August Strindberg: Im Lichte Seines Lebens und Seiner Werke 1909
Falck, August Fem År med Strindberg 1935
Falkner, Fanny August Strindberg i Blå Tornet 1921
Falkner-Söderberg, Stella August Strindberg och Fanny Falkner 1970
Ferlita, Ernest The Theatre of Pilgrimage 1971
Gassner, John; Allen, Ralph Theatre and Drama in the Making 1964 (extracts)
Gassner, John A Treasury of the Theatre: from Aeschylus to Ostrovsky Vol. 1, 1967 (contained ephemera)
Gassner, John A Treasury of the Theatre: from Ibsen to Robert Lowell Vol. 2, 1970
Geijerstam, Gustaf af Hvad vill Lektor Personne? 1887
Gustafson, Alrik August Strindberg: 1849-1912 1961
Gustafson, Alrik A History of Swedish Literature 1961
Gustafson, Alrik Den Svenska Litteraturens Historia: Före 1900 1963
Gustafson, Alrik Den Svenska Litteraturens Historia: 1900-talet 1963
Hartman, Murray. "'Desire under the Elms' in the Light of Strindberg's Influence." American Literature 33: 3 (1961)
Hedén, Erik Strindberg: en ledtråd vid studiet av hans verk 1921
Hedén, Erik Strindberg: en ledtråd vid studiet av hans verk 1926
Hedenberg, Sven Strindberg i skärselden 1961
Hellström, Victor Strindberg och Musiken 1917
Jacobs, Barry. "'Psychic Murder' and Characterization in Strindberg's 'The Father.'" Scandinavica n.d
Jacobsen, Harry Digteren og Fantasten 1945
Janni, Thérèse Dubois August Strindberg: En biografi 1972
Johannesson, Eric O. The Novels of August Strindberg: A Study in Theme and Structure 1968
Josephson, Lennart Strindbergs Drama: Fröken Julie 1965
Järv, Harry Strindbergsfejden Vol. I, 1968
Järv, Harry Strindbergsfejden Vol. II, 1968
Kärnell, Karl-Åke Strindbergs-lexikon 1969
Klaf, Franklin S. Strindberg: The Origin of Psychology in Modern Drama 1963(ephemera)
Kramer, Erich Die Bosse 1952
Lagerroth, Ulla-Britta; Göran Lindström Perspektiv på Fröken Julie 1972
Lamm, Martin August Strindberg 1961
Lamm, Martin Strindberg och Makterna 1936
Lidforss, Bengt August Strindberg och den litterära Nittiotalsreklamen 1910
Liebert, Arthur Strindberg och nutidens andliga problem 1925
Lind-af-Hageby, L. August Strindberg: The Spirit of Revolt 1913
Lindström, Hans Att Samla Strindberg 1949
Lundegård, Axel Några Strindbergsminnen, knutna till en handfull brev 1920
Lundmark, Knut Strindberg: Geniet, Sökaren, Människan 1948
Lundvall, Sten Strindberg, Nordiska Muséet och Vilhelm Carlheim Gyllensköld 197i
Meyer, Gustav Studentliv i Uppsala för Sextio År sedan 1930
Mörner, Birger Den Strindberg jag har känt 1924 (ephemera)
Mörner, Magnus Birger Mörner: Resenären 1962
Mortensen, Johan Strindberg som jag mindes honom 1931
Norrman, David Strindbergs skilsmässa från Siri von Essen 1953
Ollén, Gunnar Strindbergs dramatik 1966
Ollén, Gunnar Strindbergs dramatik: en handbok 1948
Ollén, Gunnar Strindberg i TV 1971
Paul, Arvid Min Strindbergsbok 1930
Paulson, Arvid. "The Father: A Survey of Critical Opinion of August Strindberg's Tragedies and Leading American Performances of Them during the Past Half Century." Scandinavian Studies 1965
Personne, John Strindbergs-Litteraturen och Osedligheten bland Skolungdomen 1887
Rahmer, S August Strindberg: eine pathologische Studie 1907
Schleich, Carl Ludwig Hågkomster av Strindberg 1917
Släkten Strindberg från Strinne n.d.
Smedmark, Carl Reinhold. Ed. Essays on Strindberg 1966
Smedmark, Carl Reinhold Mäster Olof och Röda Rummet 1952
Smirnoff, Karin Så var det i verkligheten 1956 (ephemera)
Smirnoff, Karin Strindbergs Första Hustru 1925
Sprigge, Elizabeth The Strange Life of August Strindberg 1949
Staaf, P Det Nya Riket och dess författare 1882
Strecher, Karl Nietzsche und Strindberg 1921
August Strindberg: 1849-1912 1962
Strindberg: eine Zeitproblem und andere psychologische Aufsätze [1920]
Svanfeldt, Henrik Katalog över Strindbergssamlingen tillhörande Henrik Svanfeldt 1949
Svensson, Harald Dikterna om Strindberg 1963
Sweling, Anthony In Quest of Strindberg 1971(ephemera)
Sweling, Anthony Strindberg's Impact in France: 1920-1960 1971
Söderström, Göran Strindberg och bildkonsten 1972
Söderström, Göran Strindbergs Måleri 1972
Taub, Hans Strindberg als Traumdichter 1945
Taub, Hans Schopenhauer und Strindberg n.d.
Tranströmer, Göran August Strindberg: Ett Minnesalbum, 1849-1949. 1949 (2x)
Uddgren, Gustav Boken om Strindberg 1912
Ulanov, Barry Makers of the Modern Theatre 1961
Valency, Maurice The Flower and the Castle: An Introduction to Modern Drama 1963 (ephemera)
Vall, Bengt V Strindbergshuset: några anteckningar 1967
Vickery, John; J'nan M. Sellery. Eds. The Scapegoat: Ritual and Literature 1972
Vinberg, Ola Strindberg och hans kvinnohat 1929
Waith, Eugene. Ed. The Dramatic Moment 1967
Weiss, Samuel A. Ed. Drama in the Modern World: Plays and Essays 1974
Westman, Gösta Strindberg i U.S.A. 1920
Wirtanen, Atos August Strindberg: Liv och Dikt 1962
Miscellaneous
All Världens Berättare 2 (1955)
Andrews, Mary Raymond Shipman The Perfect Tribute 1913
August Lindberg: En Monografi 1911
Banville, Théodore de Charming Léandre 1915
The Battle of Groton Heights 1903
Cavling, Viggo Gudindernes Strid 1933
Gamla Helsingborg's Gille 1956
Gantillon, Simon Masques: Cahiers d'art Dramatique 1924
Goodman, Kenneth S.; Stevens, Thomas W. Holbein in Blackfriars 1913
Goodman, Kenneth S. Masque of Montezuma 1912
Hendes Nåde n.d.
Jahnsson, Bengt Reserverade Platser: Dikter 1965
Johansson, Karl-Erik Bara gamla pärla 1965
Moberg, Vilhelm Allmogedramer 1929
Moberg, Vilhelm De Knutna Händerna 1939 (ephemera)
Moberg, Vilhelm Vår Ofödde Son 1945
Nirdlinger, Charles Masques and Mummers 1899
Oppenheim, James The Pioneers 1910
Lavisse, Ernest Pourqoi nous nous battons 1917
Scandinavian Studies 1954-1963
Trade Across the Seas: A Book about Elof Hansson 1959
Vetterlund, Fredrik Studier och Dikter 1901
Wallack, Lester Memories of Fifty Years 1889
Winter, William Shadows of the Stage 1892
Henrik Ibsen: Plays and Criticism
Ibsen, Henrik Brand 1898
Ibsen, Henrik Brand n.d.
Ibsen, Henrik Brand 1916
Ibsen, Henrik John Gabriel Borkman 1960
Ibsen, Henrik Kejser og Galilæer 1909
Ibsen, Henrik Peer Gynt 1913
Ibsen, Henrik Six Plays by Henrik Ibsen 1957
Brøndsted, Mogens. Ed. Henrik Ibsen: En Antologi 1956
Gran, Gerhard. Ed. Henrik Ibsen: Til Hans 70de Fødelsedag 1898
Offsite boxes & barcodes
Box 1 - Barcode: 31142042237159 Box 2 - Barcode: 31142042237167 Box 3 - Barcode: 31142042237175 Box 4 - Barcode: 31142042237183 Box 5 - Barcode: 31142042237191 Box 6 - Barcode: 31142042237209 Box 7 - Barcode: 31142042237217 Box 8 - Barcode: 31142042237225 Box 9 - Barcode: 31142042237233 Box 10 - Barcode: 31142042237241 Box 11 - Barcode: 31142042237258 Box 12 - Barcode: 31142042237266 Box 13 - Barcode: 31142042237274 Box 14 - Barcode: 31142042237282 Box 15 - Barcode: 31142042237290 Box 16 - Barcode: 31142042237308 Box 17 - Barcode: 31142042237316 Box 18 - Barcode: 31142042237324 Box 19 - Barcode: 31142042237332 Box 20 - Barcode: 31142042237340 Box 21 - Barcode: 31142042237357
Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Scandinavian literature |y 19th century.; Reprints.; Literature, Modern -- Translations; Periodicals; Theater -- History -- 20th century; Postcards.; Playbills.; Correspondence.; Strindberg, August, 1849-1912; Ibsen, Henrik, 1828-1906; Paulson, Arvid
- Series I: Correspondence
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence between Paulson and various directors, producers, actors, and publishers, 1916-1974.
  - Correspondence to various people from Paulson, re: Harriet Bosse, 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence to various people from Paulson, re: publishing and the theatre, 1916-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence between Paulson and Ben-Ali Bobker, re: The 1952 Pasadena Playhouse production of Strindberg's "The Great Highway" (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence between Paulson and Dudley Nichols, re: movie productions of Strindberg's plays, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence from various actors and writers, 1920-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence from various people, 1912-1925 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence from various people, 1926-1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence from various people, 1938-1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence from various people, 1954-1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence from various people, 1966-1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Christmas Cards (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence from various people (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence from various people (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence from Paulson, re: Strindberg Society, Strindberg statue, etc., 1923-1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series II: Manuscripts
  Series II contains the mss. of Paulson's translations of Henrik Ibsen, August Strindberg and other Scandinavian authors. Subseries A contains Paulson's translations of Ibsen, as well as miscellaneous Ibsen ephemera collected by Paulson; the ephemera includes playbills, postcards and criticism. Series II, Subseries B contains Paulson's mss. translations of Strindberg; subseries C contains the same material, this time in drafts prepared for publication. Subseries D contains Paulson's translations of Vilhelm Moberg, Knut Hamsun, Gustav Geijerstam and other Scandinavian authors. Subseries E contains miscellaneous manuscripts.
  - Subseries A: Henrik Ibsen
    - Brand: The Shrieve. Trans. Miles M. Dawson (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Bergwitz, Jon K. Henrik Ibsen: I sin Avstamning Norsk eller Fremmed?, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - The Doll's House (Act III) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Ghosts (synopsis) (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Ghosts (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Hedda Gabler (I) (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Hedda Gabler (II) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - John Gabriel Borkman (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - The Master Builder (I) (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - The Master Builder (II) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Master Olaf (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Peer Gynt (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Rosmersholm (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - When We Dead Awaken (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Ostvedt, Einar. Henrik Ibsen og hans Barndomshjem i Skien og Gjerpen; Henrik Ibsen og hans barndomsmiljo, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Biography of Ibsen (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Ibsen Memorial Committee Letterheads (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Ibsen Memorial Performance (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Playbills (var. Ibsen plays), 1935-1970 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Postcard depicting Ibsen's home near Skien, Norway (blank) (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Subseries B: August Strindberg
    - Alone (I) (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Alone (II) (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Alone (III)/ Days of Loneliness (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Alone (IV) / The Wolves Are Howling (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Alone (V) / Days of Loneliness (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Alone (VI) / Days of Loneliness (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - An Attempt at Reform (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - The Black Glove (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - The Buried Premises (I) (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - The Buried Premises (II) (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - China (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Queen Christina of Sweden (Box 4, Folder 12)